[Junior school entrance ceremony]
Got it?
Um...
Yeah.
It's really blurry.
Rin-chan! Kouki! Stand beside each other!
All right!
Kouki-kun.
Here goes.
Okay. Next, I'll get a photo of you and Rin-chan.
You don't need to get one of me.
Of course I do!
She'll grow up before you know it.
You need to keep a record of these moments.
Right.
Daikichi-san, try to relax a little.
Ashita no koto wa wakaranai
明日のことはわからない
I can't tell what'll come tomorrow.
Kore tte gisei to wa chigau
これって犠牲とは違う
This is different than making a sacrifice.
Nanika ga chigau
何かが違う
Something about it is different.
Batsu geemu ja nante omowanai
罰ゲームじゃなんて思わない
And I don't think of it as some sort of forfeit.
...tte nande na no ka wakaranai
...ってなんでなのか分からない
So I just don't get why.
Chotto shakuzen to shinai kedo
ちょっと釈然としないけど
I can't quite wrap my head around it,
Kimi no sonzai ima daiji da nante mon ja nai
君の存在今大事だなんてもんじゃない
but your existence is now much more than just important to me.
Owaranai koto nante kono yo no doko ni mo nai
終わらないことなんてこの世のどこにもない
There's nothing in this world that doesn't come to an end.
Naku no wa tsurain ja nai no
泣くのは辛いんじゃないの
I don't cry because I'm hurting.
Ai no sweet drops sweet drops
愛の sweet drops sweet drops
They're the sweet, sweet drops of love!
Zutto yume mite mitai ne
ずっと夢見てみたいね
I want to go on dreaming forever, you know?
Motto yasashiku shitai ne
もっと優しくしたいね
I want to try and be more gentle, you know?
Kimi to iraretara happy
君といられたらhappy
If I can be with you, I'm happy.
Onna no ko tte tsuyoi ne
女の子って強いね
Girls are really strong, aren't they?
Dakedo tokidoki yowai ne
だけど時々弱いね
But sometimes, they can be really weak, you know?
Bokura no negai wa happy happy happy
僕らの願いは happy happy happy
Our wishes are happy, happy, happy.
Sonna hibi mo happy
そんな日々も happy
And our days will be just as happy!
Just wanna make you happy!
Not again!
Hey, Rin! How many times have I told you not to go wandering off on your own?
Yeah...
You're a big girl now. You have to get it together.
I know...
You clearly don't!
Daikichi, can we buy this for a snack?
A snack?!
It just looked really good...
Have you never had cereal before?
Nope. I wonder if it's too much for me.
No, I don't mind buying it, but...
You're really supposed to eat that for breakfast.
It's okay to have sweets for a meal?
How should I put this? It looks like sweets,
but it's okay to have it at meal times.
You put milk on it, and...
Wow...
Maybe you can have it for breakfast tomorrow?
Yep, I will!
Do you want some too, Daikichi?
Nah. I don't feel like I've had a proper breakfast after I've had cereal.
Put the cereal in here.
Right.
You're really bad at that, Daikichi.
My hands are too dry.
You're like an old man.
TL Note: The line Daikichi uses here is from Mitokoumon, a Japanese TV drama centering around Tokugawa Mitsukuni, a prominent figure in Japanese history.
"Bite your tongue, knave!"
Ah! Mitokoumon!
Daikichi, there are cherry blossoms down here. Let's go back this way.
Sure.
They're blooming everywhere, huh?
The warm weather brings them out.
It's huge...
It's in full bloom.
How about we plant something to commemorate you starting junior school?
"Commemorate"?
I just it's sort of like a memory.
Every year, you and the tree would grow together.
Huh...
I have a tree, too, you know.
At your house?
Near my parents'.
When I was born, they planted a fragrant olive tree,
and Kazumi got a tea olive tree.
A fragrant olive tree? Is that the one that smells really good?
Yeah, that's right.
I've never heard of a tea olive tree.
Its flowers and scent are a lot more plain than the fragrant olive.
So Kazumi always made a fuss over how it wasn't fair...
...and tore the flowers off mine.
And when I said I'd trade, she said she didn't want some stupid second-hand tree.
On second thoughts, that wasn't a good memory at all.
So why am I wanting to do the same thing for Rin?
Anyway, if we're going to plant a tree, it should have pretty flowers.  That way, it'll be more fun when it blooms.
Or one with fruit you can eat.
Ah! I want a loquat!
Loquat?
Yeah, a loquat!
I already saved some loquat seeds.
You're going to grow it from a seed?
It'll be all you can eat on loquats!
Assuming it'll actually grow.
To be honest, I was actually thinking of planting a tree about your size.
So a loquat's no good?
Well, a tree takes a lot longer to grow than morning-glories and other flowers like that.
TL Note: This is a Japanese proverb meaning that each thing will happen in its own time.
It's like they say: peaches take three years.
And persimmons take eight!
You really are Granddad's kid, huh?
So how about loquats?
I don't really know, but what if it takes about ten years?
I'll wait.
By then, you'll probably me more interested in fancy sweets.
I can't imagine that...
Daikichi, hurry up!
If we don't hurry, we won't be able to eat them for ages!
Right, right...
Is this enough?
Yeah. If it's too deep, the bud won't be able to make it to the surface.
Right.
You really couldn't be more like Granddad.
Let's hope it comes out soon!
Yeah...
Rin, do you know about ninja?
Yeah. Kouki-kun said he's going to be one.
They say ninja jump over a hemp tree every morning.
And the tree keeps growing bigger and bigger, so eventually they can jump massive heights.
Why don't you try that with a loquat tree?
I will!
Like that.
Like that?
That's right.
Hey, hey! How big does a loquat tree grow?
As high as the roof of our house?
Um, well... Yeah, probably about that high.
Let's go back inside already.
Ten times more!
I wonder if it'll start growing tomorrow?
That's probably a bit early.
Got everything?
Yeah.
Ah!
They told us to get someone at home to check our timetable, too.
Man, what a pain...
Nobody ever did this for me.
Ah, she's right. It says I'm supposed to check it.
A fire?
It's probably a police car.
There was a crime?
I don't know.
Daikichi, attach this whistle to my bag.
Rin...
If someone you don't know starts talking to you, blow this really hard.
Right.
And then run and hide in someone's house. It doesn't matter whose.
Yeah.
Or a store!
Okay!
Rin! School!
Daikichi! Hurry up and get up! I'm going to be late!
Right...
Let's eat.
Let's eat!
You put milk on it.
Can't I just eat a little like this?
I guess, but...
Pet dogs eat this too, right?
That's dog food! It's just for dogs!
Really?
Of course!
Humans can't eat dog food.
Aw...
Don't look so disappointed.
Is it good?
Yep! It's yummy!
Rice balls are still my favourite, though.
It's going to take a lot to beat them, huh?
Daikichi, your phone!
Right.
Good morning!
I'm sorry, but Kouki was so excited that he just ran off to yours.
Ah, no, it's fine. We're good to go.
Rin-chan!
Right.
Kouki-kun's here!
Rin-chan!
Ah, here he is.
Yo!
Kouki-kun, you're covered in sticky willows!
You look like you've been living in the bushes like some wild animal.
I'm not an animal!
And what's with your hair?
Rin, go get a comb.
Okay!
Geez... Your backpack is all torn, too.
And I bet you've been scraping that stick along people's fences, too, huh?
Are you a psychic?!
Anyone could see that by just looking at you!
Are you sure it's not because you did it as a kid, too?
Rin, you should be getting ready!
I know!
What's that look for?
I'm going now!
Hey, wait! Wait there a seco-
What's wrong?!
Kouki-kun! Don't keep blowing it when there's nothing wrong!
Kouki-kun!
Hey! Quit blowing that!
If you keep blowing it, nobody's going to come help when you're really in trouble!
Understood?
Go on, then.
See you later!
Be careful of cars!
Okay!
Kouki-kun...
Let's go this way.
We're not supposed to take detours.
This isn't a detour. It's a short cut.
Ninjas...
...always use paths like this!
Geez...
Wow, it winds back and forth!
I know, right?
Kouki-kun! Hurry up!
There's no point taking a short cut if you're going to be slow!
That's not when you're supposed to blow it!
Kouki-kun...
That kid is a real piece of work...
I know, right?
Though, to be honest...
Most boys are like that.
Daikichi...
You should keep the ninja training to jumping over the loquat tree.
Exactly!
Ah!
That loquat tree is in commemoration of me starting school, right?
Yeah.
But your fragrant olive tree was planted when you were born.
So it's a little different, right?
I guess I don't have anything like that...
You're so smart...
I wonder if her mum bothered to plant a tree for her or anything.
I wonder if there's one at Granddad's.
Ah, yeah, Granddad might've...
But you weren't told anything about something like that, right?
No...
And Granddad's gone now.
If I don't know about it, nobody does.
I shouldn't have told her about my olive tree.
Daikichi! Your elbow's on the table again!
Right! Sorry!
Shit...
I didn't think we'd be meeting again.
Neither did I.
This is from the entrance ceremony.
Thanks.
Huh? A tree for Rin?
Ah! There is! There was!
Really?
Y-Yes, well... I think there was one...
How can you not be sure?
Souichi-san was the one who planted it.
Granddad...
I'd like to replant it at my place.
What sort of tree is it?
A small one.
No, I mean... What type was it?
And the place.
Um... It's still small.
And the branches are thin.
It's here.
Do you really draw for a living?
I draw manga, not maps.
Which way is north?
North?
The sun rises in the west, so...
You've got it the wrong way round!
Forget the directions. Just draw me one side of the street in front of the house.
Ah, I see. That's right.
Anyway, I have work, so I have to go.
Thanks for the food.
Sorry to bother you at such a busy time.
I wonder if I had a tree.
Granddad would have planted something for you.
I'm sure of it.
And if he didn't, all you need to do is plant another one.
One that's six years old.
Yeah...
Would you like to see Daikichi's tree?
Yeah, I want to see!
It's really big, huh?
It's thirty years old, after all. Just like Daikichi.
They've both gotten so big...
It's a fragrant olive, right?
That's right. I'm surprised you recognised it!
Daikichi told me.
This one is Kazumi's.
A tea olive?
That's right.
Do you remember the big tree in Granddad's back garden?
Oh, that one?
That's my tree. A tea olive.
Really?
Huh? This tree...
Granddad planted it for me when I was born.
That's the same tree as Kazumi-oneechan!
That's right.
When I was young, I always compared my height with it.
I really loved that tree, so I decided to plant another one for my daughter here.
Was that a tea olive tree?
Did Daikichi compare his height with his tree, too?
Of course!
Ah!
Long before the day we met...
Daikichi, is that...?
The leaves are the same!
It's a six year old fragrant olive.
The same as mine.
That's us done.
Oh, I forgot!
What?
It looks like I won't be able to jump over this one.
I don't think I could, either.
We didn't even know about Rin half a year ago.
I know...
Daikichi! The train's going to leave!
Coming!
I'd better go.
I'll see you to the station.
But...
Long before the day we met,
we were already drops in the same river.
Nichiyou no hareta hirusagari
日曜の晴れた昼下がり
A sunny Sunday's early afternoon;
Kyou wa doko e yukou?
今日はどこへ行こう？
where should we go today?
Kayoinareta itsumo no michi ga
通い慣れたいつもの道が
The same old road that I'm so used to walking on...
Mabushiku kagayaite mieru
眩しく 輝いて見える
...shines with a dazzling light.
Terasu atatakai taiyou to
照らす暖かい太陽と
If I have the warm sunlight shining down on me...
Tonari ni kimi ga ireba...
隣に君がいれば
...and you by my side...
Whoa! High, high, high!
Hashagidasu kimochi ni
はしゃぎだす気持ちに
My feelings are ready to burst forth.
Utae lai lai lai!
歌え lai lai lai!
Sing out, lai lai lai!
Koe wa doko made mo
声はどこまでも
My voice reaches every corner of the earth.
Mou high high high!
もう high high high!
I'm already high, high, high!
Maiagaru kaze ni nori
舞い上がる風に乗り
Riding the whirling winds...
Utae lai lai lai!
歌え lai lai lai!
Sing out, lai lai lai!
Koe mo tobihaneru
声も飛び跳ねる
My voice swoops up and down with me.
Daikichi!
What's wrong?!
What happened?!
There's some weird old guy outside!
Kouki-kun...
No, he's just...
What?!
Daikichi, it's not like that...
Where is he?!
Listen to me already!
That's Matsui-san! He's our neighbour!
Don't call him "some weird old guy"!
I'm sorry...
I'm... So... rry...
Not at all. It's my fault.
It seems I gave you quite a scare when I called out to you like that.
I'm sorry.
No, we've been terribly rude...
Take care on your way to school.
See you later!
Thank you.
When you ran away, you took Rin with you.
Huh? But Kouki-kun made a mistake.
I can rest a little easier knowing Kouki's around.
Just a little?!
Of course! You're still just a little kid!
I'm not a kid!
We're going to be late...